Finding Aid for Ann Arbor Charter Commission (Ann Arbor, Mich.: 1953-1955) records, 1938-1955
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ann Arbor Charter Commission (Ann Arbor, Mich.: 1953-1955) records 1938-1955
Ann Arbor Charter Commission (Ann Arbor, Mich.: 1953-1955)
2 linear feet.
87480 Cc.5 2
Commission established to recommend revision of the Ann Arbor, Michigan, city charter. Correspondence, petitions, 1949, requesting appointments of commissioners, minutes, financial statements, and drafts of proposed charter at various stages of revision, also recommendations of the League of Women Voters.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records came to the library from the University of Michigan Bureau of Government Library in 1967 (donor no. 2807 ).
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
In 1950 the president of the Ann Arbor city council appointed a council committee to make a study of the charter of the city which had been in effect since 1889. There had previously been a Charter Study Commission in 1942 but nothing had come of it. At about the same time as the council committee, a group of citizens formed a Citizens Committee for Charter Revision. After many hearings and public discussion, the people of Ann Arbor in May 1953 voted to revise the charter. In June 1953, nine individuals were elected to serve on the commission. The first draft of the revised draft was presented to the public on December 14, 1954. Following approval by the governor, the revised charter was put on the ballot in April 1955 where it was approved.
The records of the Ann Arbor Charter Commission of 1953-1955 also includes early materials from the 1942 Charter Study Commission and as well as other collected materials on municipal issues. The record group has been arranged into five series: Correspondence; Papers and reports; History and organizational materials; Drafts; and Miscellaneous and background materials.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Charters.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Politics and government.
- Correspondence, 1939-1955
  - 1939-1950 (Box 1)
  - 1951 (Box 1)
  - 1954 (Box 1)
  - 1955 (Box 1)
  - undated (Box 1)
- Papers and reports19381954 and undated
  - 1938 (Box 1)
  - 1939 (Box 1)
  - 1940 (Box 1)
  - 1946-1950 (Box 1)
  - 1951 (Box 1)
  - 1952 (Box 1)
  - 1953 (Box 1)
  - 1954 (Box 1)
  - 1955 (Box 1)
  - undated (Box 1)
- History and organizational materials
  - Petitions for election of commission, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1953-1955 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Charter Revision: History (Box 1)
- Drafts
  - Charter: Preliminary draft (Box 1)
  - Charter: Second draft (Box 1)
  - Charter: Third draft (Box 1)
  - Charter: Semi-final draft (Box 1)
  - Charter: Final draft (Box 1)
  - Charter: Chapter 17, employee retirement system, drafts, memoranda, etc. (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous and background materials
  - Financial statements, undated (Box 2)
  - City Budget, 1954-1955 (Box 2)
  - Municipal employees, 1942 and undated (Box 2)
  - Minutes of the Ann Arbor Board of Education, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Reports, papers, and history, of the Ann Arbor Public Library (Box 2)
  - Minutes and reports of the Charter Revision Study Commission of the Ann Arbor League of Woman Voters, 1942-1955 (Box 2)
  - Reports and recommendations of the Ann Arbor League of Woman Voters, undated (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets and publications (Box 2)
  - Maps: parks, schools, churches, roads (Box 2)
  - Clippings and papers, 1953-1955 and undated, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Scrapbooks, 1953-1955, 2 volumes (Box 2)
    (1 volume transferred from the Paul Kauper papers)